奉太郎の推理どおりなら
僕たちのkanya祭は
少なくとも一人の高校生活を代償になりたってることになるね
でも驚いたよ
何がだ
奉太郎が謎解きをしようとしたこと自体にさ
俺も　驚いた
神高入学以来
奉太郎はいくつか謎解きをしてきたよね
何でそんな面倒なことやったか理由は分かってる
千反田さんのためだろ
千反田のせいだ
それでもいい
だけど今日は違った
聞くこともできたはずなんだ　奉太郎は
今日謎を解く責任は
僕らの間で四等分されていた
分からないと言って逃げても
誰も何も言わなかったと思うんだよ
なのに
何でトイレに籠ってまで回答を見つけようとしたんだい
あれも　千反田さんのためだっだの
いい加減
灰色にも飽きたからな
千反田と来たら
エネルギー効率は悪いことこの上ない
部長職　文集作り　試験
そして過去の謎解き
よく疲れないもんだ
お前も伊原もな
無駄の多いやり方してるよ　お前らは
まあ　そうかもね
でもな
隣の芝生は多く見えるもんだ
お前らを見てるとたまに落ち着かなくなる
俺は落ち着きたい
Hyouka
だが　それでも俺は
If your theory is correct,
then the price paid for the Kan'ya Fair
何も面白いとは思えない
was that at least one student had to give up their high school life.
だからせめて
その
何だ
It surprised me, though.
推理でもして　一枚噛みたかったのさ
What?
That you actually tried to solve the mystery.
お前らのやり方にな
I was surprised too.
何か言えよ
You've solved a bunch of mysteries since we enrolled at Kami High,
奉太郎は
奉太郎はバラ色が羨ましかったのかい
but I think I know why you've gone to so much trouble.
It's for Chitanda's sake, isn't it?
かもな
More like, it's Chitanda's fault.
Whatever you say.
But today was different.
You could've bailed out.
All four of us shared the responsibility to solve today's mystery.
退屈な窓辺に吹き込む風に
Had you just given up, no one would've said a word.
顔を顰めたのは照れくさ　その裏返し
And yet...
You shut yourself in the toilet trying to figure it out. Why?
It was for Chitanda's sake, wasn't it?
KamiGami
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
There's a limit to how dull one's life can be.
Chitanda wastes more energy than anyone I've met.
曖昧に頷く掌の今日
What with her club presidency, the anthology, exams,
and solving mysteries of the past...
描いてる自分は少し大袈裟で
I'm impressed that she never gets tired.
You and Ibara too.
何かが変わりそうな気がしているよ
You always do things in such an inefficient way.
I guess.
But, you know,
心に呼びかける君のせいだね
the grass is always greener on the other side.
When I see you, it makes it harder for me to relax.
曇り空覗いた予感
I just want to take it easy.
I can't consider this stuff fun.
手を伸ばそう　いつよりも力強い勇気で
So, at least... What was it...
光も影もまだ遠くで
I wanted to just try a little bit of it, in my own way.
それでも僕らは優しさの理由が知りたい
A taste of the way you do things.
Come on, say something!
今は誰の名前でもない
So you...
So you really do long for a colorful life?
輝きの彼方へ
全部過去になる前に見つけに行こう
I might.
走过历史的古籍研究社之真相
The Truth of the Classics Club and Its Past
バラ色　か
Colorful, huh...
I wonder if that's what "colorful" means.
あれがバラ色なんだろうか
I don't know.
分からん
Chitanda investigating the past,
過去を探求する千反田
and Sekitani Jun protecting the Kan'ya Fair...
kanya祭を守った関谷純
Classics Club president Sekitani Jun
Do I really want to become like that?
あんな風に俺はなりたいのか
Do I really want a colorful life?
本当にバラ色になりたいのか
I don't know.
分からん
そもそもバラ色とは何だ
To begin with, what is "colorful"?
I don't know.
分からん
バラ色と言ったら　姉貴もそうだ
I guess my sister lives a colorful life as well.
きっと10年後　この毎日のことを惜しまない　か
"I'm sure that ten years from now, I'll be able to look back on these days without regret."
When I turn 25, I wonder how I'll look back on the past ten years.
25歳の俺は10年前をどう振り返っているだろ
I'm sure Sekitani Jun didn't regret anything.
関谷純は惜しまなかったはずだ
俺は
But I...
Oreki speaking.
はい　折木です
Is that you, Houtarou?
あれ　奉太郎
Ah, Tomoe. You're still alive?
姉貴か　生きてたのか
失礼ね
Don't be mean.
あたしが強盗の一人や二人を相手に殺されると思ってるの
You think a few robbers is all it'd take to do me in?
So that's what happened, huh?
やっぱりそういう目に遭ってたのか
Yep, when I arrived in Pristina yesterday.
昨日pristinaに入ったところ
資金健康ともに問題無し
But my wallet and my health are both fine.
次はsarajevoに入ったら手紙を書くわ
I'll send you a postcard when I arrive in Sarajevo.
以上報告終わり
Report over.
So how's it going for you?
でそっちはどう
We're working on the anthology. Hyouka.
文集を作ってる　氷菓
That's right, Hyouka!
ああ　氷菓ね
関谷純のことを調べたよ
We investigated the story of Sekitani Jun.
関谷純
Sekitani Jun?
That name brings back memories.
懐かしい名前ね
ええ　今でも伝わってるんだ
They're still talking about that, huh?
So, is the Kan'ya Fair still a taboo?
じゃ　まだkanya祭は禁句なの
Taboo
What?
何だって
It was such a tragedy. So much trouble.
あれも悲劇よね
嫌だったわ
禁句
Taboo? Tragedy? Trouble?
悲劇
嫌だった
ちょっと待ってよ
Wait a second! Are you talking about the story of Sekitani Jun?
関谷純の話だぞ
分かってるわよ
Yeah. The "kind hero" thing.
優しい英雄でしょ
Did you know about it?
あんたこそ分かってるの
いや　どうも分かってないらしい
It seems like I don't...
Tell me about Sekitani Jun!
姉貴　聞かせてくれ
関谷純のことを
I don't have time for that!
そんな暇はな―い
Later!
じゃね
こ　こ
このくそ姉貴
D-Damn you, Tomoe!
まだ終わってない
It's not over.
千反田たちに披露した俺の説
The theory I prepared and told to the others...
あれは
Either I was wrong, or it's not the whole story.
間違っているか　不十分だったんだ
もし生きていたとしたら
If he's still alive, does he regret his high school days?
関谷純は高校時代を惜しまないだろか
By my reckoning, he definitely wouldn't.
惜しむはずがないと思っていた
He was the hero who left high school, sacrificing himself for his and his friends' passion.
自らの
そして仲間たちの情熱に殉じて高校を去った英雄は
その自己犠牲を悔やんでいるはずもない
He wouldn't regret that sacrifice.
どこかでそう思い込んでいた
Or so I assumed.
だが　本当にそうだろか
But was that really the case?
たかが文化祭で学校を終われ
His high school days came to an end,
and his whole life changed, just for a culture fair.
人生の局面を変えられて
High school life is supposed to be colorful.
高校生活と言えばバラ色だ
But if those colors should burn so brightly that it breaks off midway,
だがその高校生活を途中で
打ち切ってしまうほどの強烈なバラ色は
can you still call it colorful?
それでもバラ色と呼べるのだろうか
Of course not.
そんなはずはない
仲間のために殉じてすべてを許す
Could there really be a hero who would sacrifice himself,
and then forgive everyone afterward with no regrets?
そんな英雄がそうそういってたまるもんか
Not to mention that my sister referred to it as a "tragedy".
それに姉貴はあれを「悲劇」と呼んだ
Was Sekitani Jun's high school life really that glorious?
関谷純の高校生活は本当にバラ色だったのか
I need to be sure.
突き止めてやる
Oh, Fuku!
福ちゃん
や　摩耶花も奉太郎に呼ばれたのかい
Hey!
Did Houtarou call you too?
うん　話があるから　放課後部室に来いって
Yeah. "Club meeting after class. We need to discuss something."
あの奉太郎がわざわざ人を呼び出すなんて
In all the time I've known Houtarou,
僕の記憶では前例がないことだね
I don't remember him ever calling people together like this.
私漫研の方が忙しいのに
And I'm kinda busy with the Manga Lab too...
Good afternoon!
こんにちは
Thank you very much for yesterday.
昨日はありがとうございました
ううん　私も楽しかったから
No problem.
I had fun too.
それより　奉太郎は
So, where's Houtarou?
Um...
あの
来たみたいだね
There he is.
揃ってるな
Glad you could make it.
What did you want to discuss?
話って何よ
I have an addendum to be made to yesterday's theory.
昨日の件で補足することがある
With this, it should be complete.
これで決着になると思う
Huh?
あんたね
Oh, come on...
折木さん　私
Oreki, there's still one part of this case I don't understand.
この件については
まだ知らなければならないことがあるようです
大丈夫
Don't worry.
大抵のことは今日補足できるはずだ
After this, it should be fairly clear.
Okay.
はい
What are you talking about, Oreki?
どういうこと　折木
補足って何を
What addendum?
補足は補足だ
An addendum is what it is.
不完全だったものを完全に近づけるための後付け作業だ
I'm bringing something that's incomplete closer to completion.
不完全
Incomplete?
奉太郎の説が間違ってたってことかい
Does that mean your theory was wrong?
I don't know.
分からん
方向が間違っていたのか
The premise might've been wrong from the start, or I might not have dug deep enough.
踏み込みが足りなかったのか
You don't know?
分からんって
なのにあたしたちを呼び出したの
Then why'd you call this meeting?
I can't believe this...
信じられない
Just listen.
まあ　聞け
もっと氷菓を大事にするべきだった
We should've focused more on what Hyouka said.
It says very clearly in the introduction that Sekitani Jun's tale was no epic.
関谷純の物語は英雄譚なんかじゃなかったと
はっきり序文に書いてある
But we discarded that yesterday.
それは　昨日話して除外したじゃないのか
It's just the writer's opinion, after all.
あくまで書き手の心象だからって
Yeah, but that might be misleading.
ああ　だがミスリードの可能性もある
But that's—
そんなこと言ってたら
それから
And this sentence about "battles", "sacrifices" and "his smile"...
この争いも犠牲も 先輩のあの微笑みさえものくだり
Sacrifice
この犠牲は犠牲でいいか
Are you sure this word is "sacrifice"? These characters can also mean "scapegoat".
生け贄とも読めるよな
生け贄：供神的活供品或者为他人而舍去生命或名利等
Sacrifice
Isn't "scapegoat" written with different characters?
生け贄は違う字でしょ
Scapegoat
It should start with the character for "living".
生きるって字で始まる
No, you can also read this one as "scapegoat".
いいえ　犠牲と書いても生贄と読めます
They are essentially the same thing.
本来両者は同じものです
さすがは成績上位者
I'd expect nothing less from a top student. Moving on.
話が早い
Okay, so maybe there's another way to read that word.
読み方に別海があるのが分かったよ
But if the meaning of the text depends on that,
でも　本当はどう読むのが正解かなんて
then no one but the writer knows what it really means!
それこそ書いた本人じゃないと分かるはずもないだろ
そうと思う
Exactly.
So we should just ask the writer.
本人に聞けばいい
The writer?
本人
The writer of the introduction.
序文を書いた本人さ
郡山養子
Kooriyama Youko.
45年前高校一年生で現在は60か61
If she was a first-year student 45 years ago, she'd be 60 or 61 now.
Have you been trying to find her?
探したんですか　その人
探すまでもない　すぐそばにいる
I didn't need to. She's already right under our noses.
Isn't that right, assistant librarian?
そうだな　図書員
Really?
そうなの
そう
Really.
そうって
Really?
何がそうなんですか
Really what?
家の師匠の糸魚川先生ね
Our librarian, Mrs. Itoigawa.
Itoigawa Youko.
糸魚川養子先生
Itoigawa Youko
旧姓が郡山なのね
Her maiden name was Kooriyama, wasn't it?
Kooriyama Youko
そうだ
Yeah.
あの養うって字の養子はなかなかないだろう
It's quite rare to see Youko written with the character for "nurture",
Youko
and her age fits perfectly as well.
況して糸魚川先生は年の頃も完全に適合する
Not to mention the way that she reacted, when she heard
加えて俺たちが古典部と知った時の　あの反応だ
that we were in the Classics Club.
You're really weird, Oreki.
やっぱり折木って変だよ
ずっと先生の近くにいた私でも
I'm around her all the time, but if you hadn't told me I'd have had no idea.
言われるまで気付かなかったわ
You should really just let Chi open up your skull and check what's inside.
本当にチーちゃんに頭の中を覗いてもらえば
前にも言ったが
I told you before, what you call flashes of genius are really just strokes of luck.
きらめきばかりは運が絡むからな
それで千反田に解剖されてはたまらん
I can't let Chitanda dissect me just yet.
じ　じゃ　糸魚川先生にお話を伺えば
Then, let's talk to Mrs. Itoigawa!
She knows what happened 45 years ago.
45年前のことは分かる
Why it wasn't an epic, why the cover looks as it does,
何であれが英雄譚じゃなかったのか
何であんな表紙なのか
and why the anthology has a weird title like "Hyouka"...
何で氷菓なんて奇妙なタイトルなのか
And...
そして
She knows what happened to your uncle.
お前の伯父のことも
But do you have any proof it's really Mrs. Itoigawa?
でも　本当に糸魚川先生がそうだって証拠あるのかい
Don't sweat it.
抜かりはない
I already confirmed that.
実はもう確認を取った
You asked her?
本人に
Yeah.
あ　2年生の頃は部長を務めていたとさ
I asked her if she was a club president during second year.
話を聞くアポも取ってある
I also asked her if we could talk to her later.
Well, it's about time.
さあ　そろそろ時間だ
図書室へ行こう
Let's go to the library.
You're really getting into it, aren't you?
やけに張りきってるじゃない
I guess.
まあな
夏至
阳至极热 昼至长也
Summer Solstice
As the sun shines on us the
longest, its gaze is the strongest too.
Hyouka
糸魚川先生
Mrs. Itoigawa!
ああ　古典部ね
Ah, the Classics kids.
ごめんなさい　少し仕事が残ってるの
Sorry. I've still got a bit of work to do.
話はここでもいいかしら
Can we talk here?
私　手伝います
I'll help!
ありがとう　伊原さん
Thank you, Ibara.
何が私に聞きたいことがあるそうね
I heard you have some questions for me.
Yes.
はい　その前に
But first, I'd like to confirm a few things in front of the others.
もう一度こいつらの前で確認したいんですが
糸魚川先生の旧姓は
Your maiden name was Kooriyama, right?
郡山ですね
ええ
Yes.
じゃ
Then, are you the writer of this article?
これを書いたのは先生ですね
ええ　そうよ
Yes, that was me.
でも驚いたわ
まだそんなものが残ってたのね
I'm surprised it's still around.
何を聞きたいかは大体分かったわ
I have an idea of what you want to ask me about.
あなたたち　45年前のあの運動のことを知りたいのね
You want to know about that movement 45 years ago, right?
Bingo.
ビンゴだ
She really does know about it.
やはりこの人は知っている
でもどうして今更あんな昔のことを
But why do you want to know about that now?
もう忘れられたことだと思っていたわ
I was hoping I could finally leave it behind me.
ええ　この千反田が妙なことを
We wouldn't have noticed it either, but Chitanda here is a real curiosity monster.
気にする好奇心の猛獣でなければ
俺たちも気付かなかったでしょ
She's always fixated by weird details.
好奇心の猛獣
A curiosity monster?
すみません　亡者でした
Sorry. I meant a curiosity-monger.
そ　そんな
Please!
亡者だなんて
I'm not that fixated...
あなたは
Why are you so interested in that movement?
どうしてあの運動に興味を持ったのかしら
関谷純が私の　伯父だからです
Sekitani Jun is my uncle.
あら　そうなの
Oh, I see.
関谷純さん　懐かしい名前ね
Sekitani Jun...
That brings back memories.
お元気なのかしら
How's he doing?
分かりません
I don't know.
インドで行方不明になりました
He disappeared in India.
ああ　そう
I see...
いつかもう一度お会いしたいと思っていたのに
I hoped I might be able to see him once again.
私ももう一度会いたいと思っています
I hope to be able to see him again too.
糸魚川先生
Mrs. Itoigawa, please tell us!
教えてください
45年前何があったんですか
What happened 45 years ago?
伯父の事件はどうして英雄譚じゃなかったんですか
Why wasn't my uncle's tale an epic?
どうして古典部の文集は氷菓なんですか
Why was the Classics Club's anthology called "Hyouka"?
折木さんの推測はどこまで正しかったんですか
How much of Oreki's theory was correct?
折木君の推測
Oreki's theory?
何のことかしら
What would that be?
先生
Well,
折木は断編的な資料をつなぎ合わせて
he pieced together evidence from a few sources
45年前に起きたことを推測したんです
and guessed what happened 45 years ago.
ちょっとこいつの話を聞いてやってください
Please listen to what he has to say.
じゃ　その話は司書室で聞きましょうか
Then, let's do that in my office.
Librarian's office
I see.
なるほどね
それで彼の退学は10月にずれ込んだと考えてたのね
So from this, you concluded that he wasn't expelled until October?
Yes. That's my theory.
はい　俺の推測は以上です
この資料だけで
And you worked that out using only these sources?
今の話を組み立てたっていうの
こいつらの推論をまとめただけです
I just summarized their theories.
あきれたものね
I'm quite amazed.
見当違いですか
Was I wrong?
いえ　見てきたようだわ
No, it's like you were there yourself.
Most of what you said is correct.
折木君の話した事はほとんど事実よ
このうえ　何私に聞くことがあるのかしら？
What else do you need to ask me about?
さあ　でも　奉太郎がなんだか不十分なところがあるって言うんですけど
I'm not sure. Houtarou said his theory was incomplete.
俺が聞きたいのは一つです
I have just one question.
関谷純は望んで全生徒の盾になったんですか
Did Sekitani Jun willingly become the students' shield?
全生徒の代表として　英雄らしく胸を張り
Did he stand proud as the representative of the student body,
薔薇色の高校生活に殉じて学校を去ったんですか
and leave the school heroically, sacrificing his colorful high school life?
本当に見透かされてるようね
It seems you've already figured it out.
ええ　随分昔の話だけど　今でもよく覚えているわ
It was a really long time ago, but I still remember clearly.
Back then, Kamiyama High's culture fair was our reason for living.
その頃　神山高校の文化祭っていえば
みんなの生きる目標みたいなものだった
当時　日本中にうねっていたエネルギーが
All the energy that accumulated throughout Japan at the time
神高では文化祭で形になってたっていうところかしら
burst out at Kami High in the form of the culture fair.
But the year I started high school,
でも　私が入学した年は
it got out of hand, and was more like a riot than a fair.
運動がいきすぎてほとんど暴動みたいになっていたわ
その年　当時の校長先生が発破をかけたらしいの
It was the principal who threw gunpowder onto the fire.
「寒村の寺子屋に甘んじてはいけない」って
"We should never be content with being a small and insignificant school", and so on.
それをみんなは文化祭潰しだと思ったのね
Everyone considered that an attack against the culture fair.
文化祭の日程をこれまでの五日間から二日にするって一方的通達されて
Without considering the students, they shortened the fair from five to two days.
That was the spark that ignited the whole uproar.
それが引き金になって　大騒ぎに発展した
学校中がぴりぴりしていたわ
The school was full of tension and energy.
張り紙や演説会　そして
There were many bills and speeches expressing the unified will of the student body.
学生側の統一意思を表明しようってところまで運動は進んだわ
It was quite serious, wasn't it?
真剣だったんですね
ま　今の僕たちじゃ想像もつかない世界だよね
We students today can't even imagine what it was like back then.
そんな立派な話じゃないわ
It's not worthy of admiration.
要は自分たちのおもちゃを取り上げられて
We were just kids who threw a tantrum when the adults took our favorite toy.
駄々をこねてたようなものだから
But...
そんな！
まあ　今だから言えることでしょうけどね
I guess it's easy for me to say that now.
So, opposition had formed to the shortening of the culture fair,
それで　文化祭縮小への反対運動が組織されたんだけど
リーダーには誰も立候補しなかった
but no one had volunteered to be the leader.
They were scared of retribution,
処罰が怖かったのね　なさけないはなしだけと
as shameful as that may have been.
そこで　貧乏くじを引かされたのが千反田さんの伯父さん　関谷純さんよ
So they made Chitanda's uncle, Sekitani Jun, take responsibility.
The actual leader was someone else,
実際の運営は別の人がやってたんだけど
その人表に名前を出さなかった
but they kept his identity secret.
The teachers' plan to shorten the culture fair would ultimately fail,
結局　文化祭の縮小計画は潰れるんだけど
熱にうかされて　激しく盛り上がった反対運動で私たちはやりすぎた
but with the opposition movement brought to a fever pitch,
we went too far in the end.
運動の中で　学生は授業のボイコットをうっていて
During the movement, the students boycotted their classes,
and at the peak of that,
それが一番盛り上がったとき
私達はキャンプファイアーで気勢をあげたわ
we lit bonfires to express our blazing discontent.
事件はそんな夜だった
It was on one of those nights that it happened.
格技場で火事が起きたの
The dojo caught on fire.
建物は放水で半壊してしまった
It was half destroyed by the time the fire was extinguished.
There was no way the students could justify that.
あれだけは学生側も正当化出来なかった
The school didn't involve the police,
学校は警察には介入させなかったけど
but when they brought up the incident afterwards,
後でこの件を問題にしたとき
not a single student could stand up for their actions.
反論できる生徒は一人もいなかった
To set an example,
結果的に学校側が見せしめとして退学処分にしたのが
they expelled the alleged leader of the movement, Sekitani.
Expelled
運動の名目上のリーダー関谷さんだった
私たち学生は何もせずに　ただそれを見ていた
We students did nothing.
We just stood and watched.
And yet, he remained calm to the very end.
それなのに　関谷さんは最後まで穏やかだったわ
関谷さんが自ら進んで学生の盾になったのかって聞いたわね
You asked if Sekitani became their leader willingly.
You know the answer, right?
もう答えはわかったでしょう？
それから何年か経って　なし崩しに文化祭は縮小されたわ
Over the coming years, the culture fair was shortened little by little.
Now it lasts three days.
今では三日間ね
That's the end of the story.
話はこれで終わりよ
ほかには？　何か聞きたいことはあるかしら
Do you have any more questions?
それじゃ　あの文集の表紙はそのときのことを絵にしたんですね
Then...
The cover of the anthology represents that time, right?
犬は学校側　ウサギは生徒
The dog is the school, and the rabbits are the students.
The rabbit who lured the dog away was Sekitani Jun.
犬を道連れにしたウサギが関谷純
So, the reason that the dojo is so much older than the other Kami High buildings
神高の施設の中で格技場だけがとびぬけて古いのは
is because it was rebuilt back in the '60s?
そのとき再建されたからですか
そうよ　二十年前に校舎の建て替えがあったとき
Yes. When they rebuilt the rest of the school 20 years ago,
格技場はまだ古くなかったから　そのままにされたの
the dojo was still relatively new, so they left it alone.
あの　先生
Mrs Itoigawa,
先生は「カンヤ祭」って言葉を使わないんですね
I noticed that you don't refer to it as the Kan'ya Fair.
Could it be because the actual characters that spell "Kan'ya"
ひょっとして　「カンヤ祭」のカンヤって字は
don't mean "Kamiyama",
「神山」じゃなくて　「関谷」って書くんじゃないですか
but rather "Sekitani"?
福ちゃん　どういうこと？
What do you mean, Fuku?
「カンヤ祭」の由来さ
The origin of the name "Kan'ya Fair".
英雄を称えて　「関谷祭」　その読みを変えて「カンヤ祭」
It was really named "Sekitani Fair", after their hero.
But it can also be read as "Kan'ya".
でも　その呼び名は欺瞞だよ
However, it's really all a lie.
Sekitani Jun didn't choose to become a hero.
関谷純は望んで英雄になったんじゃなかった
Anyone who knew that wouldn't call it the Kan'ya Fair.
それを知ってれば　「カンヤ祭」なんて呼び方は使わないよね
Is that true?
そうなんですか
Yes. In the Classics Club, calling it that is taboo.
ええ　その呼び名は古典部では禁句にしたの
Mrs. Itoigawa, do you know why my uncle named the anthology "Hyouka"?
先生　伯父がなぜ古典部の文集を「氷菓」と名づけたのか
先生はご存知ですか
No... When found out he was to be expelled,
いいえ　その名前は退学を予感した関谷さんが
珍しく無理を通して決めた名前なのよ
he made them use that title. It wasn't like him.
自分にはこれくらいしかできないって言ってね
He said that was all he could do.
But, I'm sorry.
でも　ごめんなさいね　意味はよくわからないの
I don't know what it means.
You don't?
わからない？
Does she really not know?
本当にわかってないのか
誰も受け取れなかったというのか
Did nobody get it?
That's such a lame message to leave.
あの　くだらないメッセージを
Hyouka
Oreki, what's wrong?
折木　どうしたのよ
わからないのか
You don't know? It should be obvious from what we just heard.
今の話しではっきりしただろう
"Hyouka" is just a stupid play on words.
氷菓ってのはくだらない駄洒落だ
駄洒落？
Play on words?
関谷純は俺たちみたいな古典部の末裔にまで
Yeah. He wanted to pass on his feelings to the inheritors of the Classics Club.
自分の思いが伝わるようにしたんだ
文集の名前なんてものに込めてな
He even made it the title of their anthology.
What do you getting at? Have you figured out what "Hyouka" means?
どういうことです？　折木さんは氷菓の意味がわかったんですか
Have you really?
本当にわかったの？
Tell us, Houtarou!
教えてよ　奉太郎
Houtarou?
奉太郎？
How would you say "Hyouka" in English?
氷菓を英語にしたらどうなる
アイスクリームですか
"Ice cream", right?
"Ice cream"? Is that the message?
アイスクリーム　それがメッセジーなの？
Like I said, it's a play on words.
だから駄洒落だと言ったろ
あの　みなさん？
Uh, what is it?
Um...
関谷純が残した本当の言葉はこれだ
This is the true message that Sekitani Jun left behind.
I... remember.
思い出しました
私は伯父に「氷菓とはなんのことか」と聞いたんです
I asked my uncle, "What does 'Hyouka' mean?"
そのとき　伯父は私に
Then... he told me...
そうです　強くなれと言ったんです
That's right!
He told me to be strong.
もし私が弱かったら
Because if I was weak,
悲鳴も
I wouldn't be able to...
そう　悲鳴も上げられなくなる日が来るって
A day... A day would come when I wouldn't even be able to scream!
I'd be alive, but...
そうなったら　私は生きたまま
私は生きたまま死ぬのが怖くて泣いたんです
Inside, I'd really be dead. I cried because that idea terrified me.
I'm so glad...
よかった　思い出せました
I finally remembered!
Now I can truly say goodbye to my uncle!
これで　ちゃんと伯父を送れます
It's all thanks to you, Oreki.
折木さんのおかげです
ありがとうございます　折木さん
Thank you, Oreki!
Well... It was just by chance.
いや　まあ　たまたまだ
はい　たまたまですね
Yes, by chance.
"I scream."
アイ　スクリーム
私は叫ぶ…　か
From the bottom of my lungs.
Huh...
So, I prepared the content draft for the anthology, and the schedule as well.
で　文集の台割とスケジュールをざっくり作ってみたんだけど
Ah, so this is what a content draft looks like!
台割ってこう書くんですね
すごいです　摩耶花さん
You're amazing, Mayaka!
R-Really?
そ　そう？
But where did you learn how to do that?
でも　どこでこんなことを覚えたんですか
Does it really matter?
それは　まあ　いいじゃん
なあ　この「優しき英雄事件」
Hey!
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
This special, "The Kind Hero Incident: Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago".
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
四十五年前の隠された真相」とかいう特集記事なんだが
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
Special:
The Kind Hero Incident:
Hidden Truth from 45 Years Ago
14 pages
What about it?
なに
Why am I writing it?
なぜ俺が執筆担当なんだ？
折木が解いた謎なんだから　折木が書くのが筋でしょ
You solved the mystery, so you should be the one writing about it!
一番ページ数が多い
It's the longest one!
そりゃそうだよ　なんにしろ目玉記事なんだからね
Of course! It's the main article!
大丈夫ですか　折木さん
Is it all right, Oreki?
大変そうなら　私が書いてみますけど
If it's too much trouble, I could try writing it.
お～　それは
That sounds...
You mustn't, Chi!
だめよ　千ぃちゃん
He's only useful at times like these!
こういうときくらいしかこいつの使え道なんてないんだから
ははは　そうそう
Yep. Let's drive him hard.
扱き使ってあげないとね
Less time complaining, more time planning!
文句言ってないで　折木もちゃんと構成考えといてよね
Ah, about your part, Fuku...
それより　福ちゃんの担当するコラム…
I wasn't expecting that, though.
でも　意外でした
何が？
Expecting what?
文集の記事です 結局引き受けてくれましたよね
That you'd actually agree to write that article for the anthology.
It's more like, I wasn't able to get out of it.
引き受けたというより　逃げ切れなかっただけだ
ま　関谷純への手向けくらいにはなるか
Well, at least this way I can pay my respects to Sekitani Jun.
それより　意外といえば
But as long as we're talking about the unexpected...
Yes?
はい？
When I told you to ask Satoshi and Ibara for help,
前　「里志と伊原にも協力を求めたらどうか」と言っただろう？
at first you resisted, but eventually you gave in.
最初は渋ってたのに　どうして急にその気になったんだ？
What made you change your mind?
Ah, well...
ああ　それは
It was what you said back then.
あのとき折木さんは言いましたよね
That even if we didn't solve my uncle's mystery, it would just be ancient history one day.
「伯父の謎が解けなくても　いつかは時効になっていくのかも」と
Ten years into the future, I probably won't care about these things any more.
確かに　十年後の私は気にしないのかもしれません
But the feelings I'm experiencing here and now...
でも　今感じた私の気持ち
それが　将来どうでもよくなってるかもなんて
I don't want to think that
they won't matter at all in the future.
今は思いたくないんです
私が生きてるのは今なんです
I'm living in the present.
だから
So...
Sorry,
すみません　まだよくわからないんです
I don't really know it myself.
いいさ　俺も同じだし
It's okay.
I'm the same.
まあ　とにかくお疲れ
Anyway, see you.
はい　では
Yeah,
see you!
折木供恵殿
Dear Oreki Tomoe,
I write to you with these questions:
聞きたいことがあって手紙を送る
姉貴は古典部のことをどこまで知っていたのか
How much do you really know about the Classics Club?
どういうつもりで俺を古典部に入らせたのか
What did you intend by making me join?
姉貴なら　俺のスタイルを知っているだろう？
You're my sister, so you know my lifestyle.
そう　省エネだ
I save energy.
If I hadn't joined the Classics Club,
古典部に入らなければ　このスタイルを見つめなおすことさえしなかった
I wouldn't have even thought to reconsider my lifestyle.
Did you anticipate that it would shake my worldview like this?
姉貴は　俺が古典部へ入ることで
そういう揺さぶりを受けることを予想していたのか
Not to mention, Hyouka.
そして　氷菓
Ever since we learned Sekitani Jun's story from that anthology,
あの文集を通して　関谷純の事件を知って以来
まあ　自分のこのスタイルも悪くないと思うようになった
I've started to think my style isn't all that bad either.
あ　いや　あくまで相対的な話だが
Of course, this is all just subjective.
But this would mean she's...
しかし　これでは　まるで姉貴は
Nah, no way.
まさかね
ここまで書いたのは　すべて近況報告だと思ってくれ
Consider what I wrote above to be my report of recent events.
いい旅を
Have a nice trip.
アドバイス　ありがとう
Thanks for your advice.
Oreki Houtarou.
折木奉太郎
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Next time: To Commit a Grave Sin.
To Commit a Grave Sin
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
まどろみの約束
芽生えてた温もり　暖かくて戸惑う
こんな気持ちをまだ　あなたは分からないよ
そんな視線には意味なんて　別にないはず
だって友達にしてるのと同じ
明け方に消えてく　小さな願星
夜の間だけの魔法を…
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
まどろみの約束
次回　大罪を犯す